<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>CNotes - make a note! - User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

      <surname>Dimitrov</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>compojoom.com</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>31.07.2012</pubdate>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the CNotes extension. It does not
      cover any other extension available on compojoom.com .</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <article>
    <para><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>CNotes - 1.0.0 - Revision 0.1</revnumber>

          <date>18.09.2012</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>

          <revremark>1st Draft</revremark>
        </revision>
      </revhistory></para>
  </article>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introducing CNotes</title>

      <para>CNotes is a Joomla! extension &amp; module that lets your users
      create private notes on each &amp; every page of your site.</para>

      <para>CNotes was developed as part of the "<ulink
      url="http://dothewebinar.com">Joomla extension development
      masterclass</ulink>" in July 2012. Together with our students we've
      explored the Joomla framework and have build something that is hopefully
      useful to you as well! If you want to learn how to build Joomla
      extensions on your own, maybe you should visit dothewebinar.com and book
      the next free webinar!</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Features</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>add private notes on every page of the site (provided that
            the cnotes is published on that pages)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>notes are added without page refresh</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>user can add/edit/delete notes in the frontend</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>administrator can view/edit/delete notes in the
            backend</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation and updates</title>

    <para>Installing CNotes is no different than installing any other Joomla!™
    extension on your site. You can read the complete instructions for
    installing Joomla!™ extensions on the <ulink
    url="http://help.joomla.org/content/view/1476/235/">official help
    page</ulink> .Throughout this chapter we assume that you are familiar with
    these instructions and we will not duplicate them.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting the installation packages</title>

      <para>You can download the latest installation packages by visiting our
      site at <ulink
      url="https://compojoom.com">https://compojoom.com</ulink>. Go to
      Download -&gt; CNotes menu item. The releases are listed in descending
      order with the newest release always on top. Click on the release number
      and then download the ZIP package.</para>

      <para>The installation package can be installed on Joomla 2.5 . You can
      use the installation package to update from previous version as well;
      just install it, without uninstalling the old package.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Updating to the latest version</title>

      <section>
        <title>Checking for the latest version and upgrading</title>

        <para>You can easily check for the latest published version of Cnotes
        by visiting https://compojoom.com and going to
        Downloads-&gt;CNotes.</para>

        <para>Updating CNotes to the latest version is by no means different
        than installing the component! You do not have to uninstall the
        previous version; in fact, you are discouraged from doing so. Simply
        follow the installation instructions so as to install the latest
        CNotes version over the existing installation. That's all! All your
        settings are preserved.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Live update</title>

        <para>There is also an alternate update path, if your server supports
        it. It is called the "Live Update" feature (thanks to Nicholas K.
        Dionysopoulos from http://akeebabackup.com) . Whenever you click on
        the Live update button in the Navigation toolbar, it will
        automatically check for the existence of an updated version and it
        will notify you. Clicking on the update button allows you to perform a
        live update without further interaction. Do note that if your server
        is protected by a firewall you'll have to enable port 80 and 443 TCP
        traffic to https://compojoom.com for this feature to work
        properly.</para>

        <para><graphic fileref="images/live-update.PNG"/></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the CNotes component</title>

    <para>Congrats! It seems that you have the first step - the installation
    behind you! Now to allow your users to add notes you should go to
    Extensions -&gt; Module Manager and here you should publish the CNotes
    module. The module should not be published to the general public, but to
    your registered users!</para>

    <section>
      <title>The Backend</title>

      <para>Once logged into your Joomla backend you can access the component
      by clicking on Components -&gt; CNotes . You'll be presented with a list
      of all notes entered by your users. Using the edit &amp; delete buttons
      at the top you can edit &amp; delete any note you want. </para>

      <graphic fileref="images/cnotes-notes-backend.PNG"/>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Frontend</title>

      <para>If you have the CNotes module published your users will be able to
      write notes and view the notes that they wrote on any page. Now on each
      page they can see only the notes that they wrote there. If you want to
      make their live easier you can provide them with a link to all their
      notes. To do so you have to create a new menu link. In the Joomla
      backend go to Menus -&gt; Your-menu-&gt; "Add new menu item" . In the
      "menu item type" field click on Select and then click on "User notes".
      (make this link available only to user registered users). Now when you
      click on the link you should see screen similar to this one (provided
      that you've written any notes)</para>

      <graphic fileref="images/cnotes-your-notes-frontend.PNG"/>

      <para>Clicking on the delete button will delete the note. Clicking on
      the title will send the user to the page where he wrote the note. And
      clicking on the title will bring them to a screen where they can edit
      their note: </para>

      <graphic fileref="images/cnotes-edit-note-frontend.PNG"/>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the CNotes Module</title>

    <para>The CNotes module allows your users to create new notes in the
    frontend of your sites &amp; it also gives them a quick look at the notes
    that they've written on the page that they are currently on. To publish
    the module you'll have to login into your Joomla Backend -&gt; go to
    Extension manager -&gt; Module manager. Here click on new and then look
    for "CNotes - user notes" -&gt; select the desired position and publish
    the module to your registered users. </para>

    <graphic fileref="images/cnotes-add-new-note.PNG"/>

    <graphic fileref="images/cnotes-note-on-page.PNG"/>

    <para>If the user has a note on the current page the module will show him
    that note. If you click on the title of the note you'll be presented with
    an edit screen and you'll be able to modify your note. </para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Tips &amp; tricks</title>

    <para/>

    <section>
      <title>SEF &amp; non-SEF urls</title>

      <para>When the user browses to a specific page we try to show him the
      notes that he has on that page. We do that by comparing the current URL
      with anything in the CNotes table that matches that URL &amp; user id.
      That works in 99% of the cases, but if your URL scheme changes for some
      reason (like you go from non-SEF URL to SEF URL, or you start to use a
      new SEF extension) the module won't be able to properly match the notes
      for the page. However -&gt; the user will be still able to see the notes
      in the "User notes" view of the component. </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Where to go from here?</title>

    <para>If you encounter any problems or have any suggestions don't hesitate
    to contact us. We provide top-notch <ulink
    url="https://compojoom.com/forum/cmc-mailchimp-for-joomla">forum
    support</ulink>. Just drop us a line!</para>

    <para>If you know a little bit of PHP &amp; MySQL maybe it is time to
    become a Joomla developer? The CNotes extension was developed during our
    webinar "<ulink url="http://dothewebinar.com">Joomla extension development
    masterclass</ulink>" - why don't you <ulink
    url="http://dothewebinar.com">join the next class</ulink> and learn how to
    develop your own notes extension???</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
